## KATHLEEN C. SAKURA

4316 Atherton Way NW Albuquerque, NM 87120 Tel: (c) 703-678-1443

E-mail: kathleen.sakura@jksgs.com

**Security**: Granted access to Top Secret information and Sensitive Compartmented Information based on Single Scope Background Investigation dated 28 March 2007.

Summary of Qualifications: Twelve years Senior Executive leadership experience in Strategic Planning, Global Intelligence Planning and Operations, Program Management, and Change Management under adverse conditions. Proven record and outstanding reputation for developing pathfinder air, space, and cyberspace intelligence and business strategies, while building new organizations and leading high performing military and civilian teams of all sizes. Over 23 years of Air Force and Joint Military experience; more than 18 years as a well-respected, highly decorated Intelligence Professional, and 5 years as a DoD Acquisition Professional certified in three areas: Program Management; Financial Management; and Research and Development. Recognized authority on Acquisition-Intelligence's genesis, and a visionary leader concerning options for the way ahead. Brings an extensive background in strategy development and policy formulation supporting National Security objectives on a global scale. Considerable expertise coordinating interagency issues and National Intelligence Community (IC) matters with senior policy decision-making and oversight fora. Brings specific analytical and intelligence operational experience in Europe, Korea, China, South Central Asia, Africa, and the Homeland.

## **Experience:**

Founding Partner, JKS Global Solutions, LLC

2012 - Present

A Small, Woman Owned, Disabled Veteran Business Formed in Fall 2012. Provides Senior Executive leaders with independent insights on Strategic Planning, National Security Matters, and Global Intelligence Planning/Operations. Helps companies and individuals reach their greatest potential through: creating purposeful partnerships while growing business opportunities in both public and private sectors.

- Provided year-long strategic advisory services to the Sr Executive team at a nationwide engineering and software services company, resulting in award of a multi-year \$960M DoD advanced intelligence and software development contract.
- Guides small and medium sized companies through growth strategies, especially how best to plan and posture for entry or expansion into the IC.
- Advises local community advocacy groups on how to best understand, posture, and advocate for retained DoD work, to include identification and characterization of projected growth areas for Intelligence, Surveillance, and Reconnaissance.

Commander, National Air and Space Intelligence Center, Wright-Patterson AFB, OH

2010 - 2012

- Led the Air Force and DoD Center of Excellence for integrated air, space/missile, and cyberspace all-source intelligence production and data analysis. Shepherded the Center's Global Enterprise comprised of 3,100 personnel through a wide-sweeping organizational change. Overcame significant resistance to change both within and outside the organization. Quickly brought Senior leadership on same strategic path; resulted in more unity of effort concerning use of operating budget of \$375M and \$2.1B facilities
- Developed and implemented advanced organizational controls to evaluate and measure overhead costs, cutting Center overhead to 11 percent, 20 points below the AF or DoD average
- Drove development of the Center's first long term (10 year) Strategic Plan, designed to shape, rather than react to considerably uncertain fiscal and global security futures
- Developed first-of-its-kind Outreach Plan, designed to improve customer, stakeholder, and resource provider perceptions. Significantly broadened understanding of the organization's mission, capabilities,

- and brand in accordance with the Strategic Plan. Resulted in a 15 percent increase in mission funding during FY2012, a year in which most DoD organizations saw a net loss of funding
- Oversaw strategy & execution for Planning & Direction, Collection, Processing, Analysis & Production, and Dissemination (PCPAD) of over 70 air, space, and ground-based intelligence sensors
- Oversaw integrated Technical Signals Intelligence, advanced Geospatial Intelligence, Measurement and Signatures Intelligence, Open Source Intelligence, Human Intelligence, and Foreign Materiel Exploitation (FME), and original all-source intelligence analysis on high technology matters
- Drove development of strategies for Air Force Intelligence, Surveillance, and Reconnaissance (ISR) Enterprise-wide solutions to meet potential future ISR and operational needs in an anti-access/area denial environment

<u>Chief of Staff of the Air Force Fellow, Office of the Secretary of Defense</u>

2009 – 2010

Military Assistant to the Chairman, Defense Business Board; The Pentagon, Washington D.C.

- Provided personal advice and counsel to the Chairman, Defense Business Board
- Led 25 private sector global business experts, developed and provided independent recommendations to the Secretary of Defense on a wide range of the Secretary's toughest strategic issues
- Coalesced best practices of highly credentialed private sector Senior Executives. Brokered delicate talks with interagency, private sector, and international thought leaders

<u>Chief of Staff of the Air Force Fellow,</u> Department of Homeland Security (DHS) 2008 – 2009 Senior Special Assistant & Military Advisor to the UnderSecretary for Intelligence and Analysis, DHS

- Provided personal advice and counsel to the UnderSecretary for Intelligence & Analysis, Department
  of Homeland Security. Influenced intelligence policy and operations for five components in the US
  government's third largest agency
- Champion for sweeping changes to DHS acquisition policy; a first to develop/propose policies which integrate intelligence supportability concerns across (and at onset of) program acquisition lifecycles

<u>Deputy Director, Joint Staff Intelligence</u> Support and Deputy Director for Intelligence
National Military Command Center, Joint Chiefs of Staff, The Pentagon

2006 – 2008

- Led 100+ highly credentialed intelligence and operational planners, directly framing decisions made by: the Director of Intelligence; the Chairman, Joint Chiefs of Staff; and the Secretary of Defense
- Championed Joint Urgent Operational Needs, and scoped pre-ISR Task Force solutions to meet critical warfighter needs, delivering \$662M of additional ISR capabilities for the warfighter

# Commander, 24th Intelligence Squadron, Ramstein Air Base, Germany 2003 – 2005

- Stood up Distributed Ground Station Four (DGS-4), and other globally-networked Command and Control capabilities used to exploit data from both Airborne and Overhead ISR sensors
- Won Europe's outstanding intelligence organization award within one year of organization stand up

#### **Education:**

— w v v v v	
Bachelor of Science in Aerospace Engineering, Auburn University, Auburn, AL	1988
Master's of Business Administration, University of Texas at San Antonio, TX	1993
Master's Degree in Military Operational Art and Science, Distinguished Graduate,	
Air Command and Staff College, Air University, Maxwell AFB, Montgomery, AL	2001
Master's Degree in National Security and Strategic Studies, with Academic Distinction,	
Air War College, Air University, Maxwell AFB, Montgomery, AL	2006
TO A TO A LOCAL COLUMN	

### **Executive Leadership and National Security Studies:**

2007
2008
2010